hello and welcome
we're in cohort 2 of the par
at all textbook group
we are in our final discussion on
chapter 10 the last of the
topical discussions
so we'll see where it goes then next
week will be the final meeting of this
cohort
where we'll have unrecorded feedback
discuss some project ideas and so on so
this will be the last recording in this
series for cohort 2. and please go to
Future textbook groups to fill out the
feedback form
and or share the link to register for
future cohorts
that being said let us turn to chapter
10.
and then
go wherever people are interested so
Michael maybe you can restate what
area you want to look at and then let's
see if it relates to anything in 10.
yeah okay so so my question was related
to related to priming
um effect so priming is uh very much
used Paradigm in Psychology which
assumes that a stimulus activate somehow
a network of semantic related items or
phonetic or somehow related items which
facilitates recognition of successive
items and then according also action and
I was wondering
um how this is represented in active
inference because it's a kind of an
action perception Loop and how the
difference between more conscious or
more higher level or kinds of decisions
um are distinguished in this active
inference framework whether we have a
possibility to distinguish between these
kinds of more priming action perception
loops and more consciously
activated action perceptions
are there any any papers is there any
research to
um
that somehow Maps those different
distinction these distinctions into the
um the terminology that we have in
active inference
do you know
yep
um Ollie any thoughts
um nothing immediately comes to mind but
um you go on please and then I'll think
if I can add to it later
okay
one
this one appears to at least address
attentional priming
in the context of motor Behavior
um I'll add the link into the the notes
section
um
but I think as we're coming to see the
framework is going to be minimally
opinionated on complex
extremely heterogeneous cognitive
phenomena like priming
you can construct a cognitive model
that embodies that through any number of
ways like you can imagine a
um nested perceptual model
where
um the first the higher level is what
genre of movie We're watching comedy or
horror and then the stimuli are the
sounds
and then like
hearing a laugh
uh then updates the belief that it's a
comedy not a horror
and then that makes certain stimuli more
attended to in the future
but that wouldn't be like an opinionated
Act of inference
framework describing how priming is
approached but rather a way that you
could use
the kinds of techniques that we
discussed in the textbook
to write your own generative model that
has some of the features that you'd like
and I'm not exactly sure how they've
done it in this
motor
paper
all the way from 2011.
Ollie anything
yeah I just I wanted to add that
um
I'm not sure if it directly relates to
this specific question or not but
um at least
I haven't seen much paper doing uh
direct empirical uh experiments trying
to
um I mean trying to observe or
verif confirm uh some of the uh ideas of
active inference framework in other
words most of the papers in the in the
literature are mostly concerned with
modeling the existing experimental data
or empirical data and but there are some
important works that's been being done
and not directly
trying to prove or confirm the active
inference framework but they have done
some
research in other areas but they've used
active inference in the modeling of the
phenomena being observed or studied so
in this case also I
um I vaguely remember seeing some
related studies that's being done and
ultimately modeled with active inference
framework but I'm not sure if there's
anything
specifically uh putting active inference
claims as hypothesis and trying to
confirm those hypothesis
well
sorry go ahead
yeah so so as you said active inference
is uh it's not a cannot be
falsified so it's it's not really a
hypothesis in this way no
but I was wondering so
um there are these different
variables that we have in this framework
for instance we have priors
on hidden States
uh code something like this
be interpreted as a primed
SS as a prime something that facilitates
successive action
vasos for instance then we have habits
or we have preferences
which might
reflect more
conscious kinds of decisions
would it make sense to think about the
distinction this way well
you go for it
um yeah just uh about the first point
you mentioned uh actually
uh it's fep that's uh because of it's
being a kind of principle uh is
inherently unpalsifiable but active
inference at least as far as I
understand it is totally falsifiable
Theory so for instance
we have some work done by
um
Daniel what was the name of the the
Japanese research is
if I'm not mistaken right yes which is
isomer yeah uh which I've tried to find
some neural correlates correlates that
uh for for some of these uh active
inference uh or some of the claims I
made within active inference framework
uh and also there are other various
studies uh that um show shows uh the
psychological evidences uh evidence for
um
those claims happening actually
happening uh in the model in the
organism or agent of Interest so that's
about the first point uh but
um I actually forgot
the second point you make so
um if you don't mind to reiterate it
yeah so I was wondering whether those
different kinds of variables that we
have for instance uh priors on hidden
States and then we have habits and
preferences and all this so on in
different places they sneak into this
whole framework and whether they could
be associated with those different kinds
of cognitive processes so for instance
that we have priors which uh condition
somehow the sequence of States
whether this could be
interpreted as a prime
that facilitates certain kinds of
activities of states that follow whereas
for instance preferences or habits are
more long-term
kinds of
entrenched routines and that could be
maybe
reflect more conscious kinds of
processes something like this would it
make sense to see it in this way
so
um but first the falsification so the
principle cannot be falsified and then
active inference might be being deployed
in a way where somebody is looking to
explore whether it's adequate or not for
a given setting
or it can merely be deployed where it's
not even being
tested against Alternatives or evaluated
as a framework itself but merely being
used to explain data
um
the different variables and the
interpretation of cognitive phenomena is
the whole point of cognitive modeling so
the prior in terms of it conditioning or
initiating inferences on hidden States
is what that variable does in the model
um
however there are a lot of open uh
interpretations on like what is
awareness and what is consciousness and
all these other questions about time
scale
like someone could argue that the slower
things are not aware of
but in the end it's really going to come
down to just writing the generative
model
and then
it can be seen in figure 4.3 there's no
consciousness awareness metacognition
etc etc so the phenomena that the that
this basal module
provides
are actually quite flexible which is why
pumdps are are broadly used even outside
of actimp
but they don't necessarily
tackle the hard problem or anything like
that
so mapping it to what is experienced
is certainly an area of of open work
but understanding how different
cognitive phenomena arise in a model
from the interplay of different
parameters is what cognitive modeling is
foreign
and there's very few attempts to
try to relate
this to this kind of psychological
research
or these kinds of psychological models
um it depends what you would mean by a
lot like for example Association of
precision or variance estimators with
anxiety
has been done in theory and in practice
and Association of different
parametric evaluations with different
um cognitive States and pathologies is
reviewed
in table 9.1
so
parameters are mapped to cognitive
States
that's why this kind of modeling is done
but that doesn't mean that the framework
has One Singular way
of interpreting it it's like you could
make a linear model
that does this or that and you could
test whether there's an effective this
condition on that outcome
but you'd be talking then with your
referent as the system of Interest
not with your referent as somehow like
confirming or disconfirming something
about linear models
so that's why
there are papers that just use active
inference modeling to explain data
like everything that Ryan Smith is doing
everything that we see in table 9.1
but in an although sometimes those kinds
of studies are taken as evidence for
active inference
like look at these papers that use
active inference empirically
and they do
um support the notion that active
inference can be used empirically
but in these cases there might be some
but I I don't think most of them are
this way they're not necessarily
comparing
continuous time generative models in
ocular motor syndromes versus an
alternative model
such a comparison would put it more
clearly into the category of like unique
explanation prediction value
of active inference as opposed to other
proposed which is to say hypothesized
cognitive models
but without comparison of multiple
methods in a paper
it's not evidence for that framework
it just it's evidence that that
framework can be used
and the the mapping of cognitive
phenomena
to parameters
is um sometimes seems pretty clear
other times especially if one is getting
into more uh complex models
it's not going to be localized to like a
single parameter because the cognitive
phenomena will arise from different
interacting
parameters
like Well when the learning rate on B is
low then
this or that
irregularity gets partitioned this way
but when the learning rate on B is high
then this might happen in this
environmental setting
but again there's so many conditioning
factors
that at the level of of abstraction
across all possible possible cognitive
models
it's only
right and good that active inference
doesn't have such a one-to-one mapping
between parameters and phenomena
if there were such a mapping we wouldn't
have the expressivity
to generate complex models
and cognitive phenomena have many
manifestations and many
um
factors that influence them
there's some promising avenues for that
but I'll keep it more focused on the
textbook for here
so okay thank you thank you with respect
to this Marvin Minsky quote in general
we are least aware of what our minds do
best
and which of these aspects are mapped on
to experiential awareness
well
you could create
multiple possible structural alternative
cognitive models so I wonder if people
are experiencing the o
I wonder if they're experiencing the
hidden State I wonder if they're
experiencing B
I wonder if and then you could design
the right experiment or maybe the data
already exists
where you you show something and you say
now what did you remember about that or
what was your experience while that was
happening
and you could find out and then you
could
evaluate and falsify one of those
structural models
or you could take a more Bayesian
approach and just describe the base
factor or the posterior model
probability across those structural
alternatives
Ollie
yeah that's a completion by Minsky also
Maps perfectly I think with Mark zomes's
claim on page 303 of his book in Spring
which claims that uh briefly we only uh
need Consciousness or at least are aware
of our Consciousness when we're trying
to
correct for the the uh more Divergent uh
Divergence between our priors and uh our
perception so
um in other words Consciousness is
something that's required for that uh
correction or belief updating and uh as
more correct as more
um
precise our predictions uh become the
less we'll need our awareness of our
consciousness
interesting that makes me think about
the Flow State like uh sent mahali
and the kind of
awareness associated with
automatic
performance
but that's that's on the path towards
empirical and experimental phenomenology
again with all of the report biases and
challenges associated
and once you got to that point of
specifying just like figure 9.1 with the
um
the person and the and showing them
different colors and then the
self-report and here's the input and
output
it wouldn't be making claims about
active inference overall let alone the
fep
again any more than some extensively
developed multilinear model
for healthcare data is making claims
about linear modeling
they're like kind of
they're related
but
evidence of one is not the same type of
evidence for the other
but here they are going to abstract away
from the specific active inference
models and focus on integrative aspects
so now we're in the space of integrative
models of
cognition and behavior and so with
respect to that
if we merely see an area for
improvements of active inference great
then we're active inference researchers
but
it also makes sense to ask what is
active inference being compared with
and because of the unifying scope being
so vast
it's hard to even
conceptualize our name
some alternative
unified perspective
but there are unifying things that might
just be like even more General that end
up being less helpful like just saying
well it's computation or it's
information you know memory is is
information perception is information
that might not be
um
differentiated enough
whereas hopefully the positioning of
active inference is on one hand unifying
diverse cognitive phenomena in different
systems
but on the other hand not so Bland and
generic
that it's equivalent to just saying you
know physics did it
this book offers a systematic account of
the theoretical underpinnings and
practical implementations of active
inference
do you fellows agree with that or how
does that claim strike you
not so much practical but systematic and
theoretical yes I would think
thanks I I broadly agree
they're going to summarize the previous
chapters
chapter one
organisms or religious things engage in
adaptive Exchange
which from a cybernetics perspective we
can frame in terms of action and
perception
and they laid out the two roads
low road
we're using Bayesian statistics
High Road
things must
from the outside
at least be re-measurable
if it's not re-measurable it doesn't
have a stable identity from the outside
to an observer
that's like the low bar on the high road
if the volatility is so high that the
thing is changing and not being what it
is then it isn't that
and then the high bar on the high road
is that actions must actually be taken
to persist
and whether those actions are trivial
or not is another question that's where
we get into that taxonomy of things with
the um path integrals paper
but just broadly low road we're using
Bayesian statistics
is there really a modern alternative
High Road
we're at least asking for repeated
measurements if not adaptive action for
persistence
again
uncontentious
chapter 4 approaches the generative
models in active inference
exact Bayesian inference
may be implausible
so they very rapidly move to variational
inference as one approach to approximate
challenging Bayesian statistical
settings
commonly used outside of active
inference uncontentious
even the use of a variational free
energy is uncontentious energy-based
learning evidence lower bound
now being applied
to a comprehensive generative model that
includes perception cognition and action
thus unifying for example signal
processing on the inbound and control
theory on the outbound
chapter 5.
they went through three mammalian
nervous system examples
and gave a little bit of information on
each of those systems in isolation
and then in the concluding figure
wired them together
to show how cortical inference
could
um play a role in dopaminergic tone of
the basal ganglia which could then
modulate the trade-off between Reliance
on habit
or conversely on
expected free energy based updating of
action priors into action posteriors and
then the ways that those selected action
policies could then be enacted through a
kind of simple differential mechanism in
the spinal cord
from an epistemic perspective what else
would you fellows have wanted to see in
the first half of the book
again considering that chapters one
through five were like
the theory and the underpinnings
and seeing this as just the first
version of what it can be
epistemically what else might be
important to include in these chapters
whether it's just a micro Edition like
oh they could have added this citation
or this variable or whether you have a
more structural comment
I'll let you go for it
I'm not sure if I've said this before or
just talked about it casually but in my
opinion some of the materials from
chapter 10 uh could be moved to some of
the earlier chapters in order to give a
kind of bigger picture in which active
inference fits so uh reading the first
chapters uh the reader at least in my
view doesn't get so much
um
I mean it doesn't learn about the
historical context of the ideas uh as as
much as needed because
frankly enough
reader
um
uh I suppose will not be familiar too
much with active inference framework
because uh obviously it's relatively uh
new framework so uh it might help them
to see the distinction between active
inference and the other earlier
Frameworks such as Bayesian brain
hypothesis predictive coding predictive
processing and so on
um and uh yeah just
see how active inference
it fits within that bigger
yes thank you Ali
what do you think about reading chapter
10 first
outlining all the challenges that was
the ideal I guess
yeah exactly wow
unbelievable
we could try it
we could try it Michael
yeah we cannot we cannot really know
because we did it the other way around
so but you can maybe try it in the next
cohort not to see how that works out for
you
yeah that would be a funny frame like
we're gonna read chapter 10 so truly do
not worry about the earlier references
they might mention an earlier chapter
again you don't have to worry because
you won't have Reddit
but this is where we're going
now you've been there
that's the big picture
and now we're going to work
forwards via backwards
to get to that integrative
um conclusion
and then we can ask whether that
um was reached was that where we wanted
to go
and did we reach it with integrity
but it's not going to be a math test
I think that makes sense
to go that way
interesting
because this is so epistemic and 10 is a
relatively long chapter
with no equations
no figures
and so
in that way it's like a super version of
chapter one
including bringing up many of the same
ideas
so definitely for our consideration
in the coming weeks
okay in chapter six there was a this is
the pragmatic section of the book
allegedly
chapter six provided a recipe
I'm sure we had many questions about
what else was happening at that
restaurant and a little bit more detail
from the sous chef and all of that
but a recipe was provided
which we can continue to build out
and they just buzzed through chapter
seven eight nine
in review merely saying that seven and
eight focused on discrete and continuous
time generative models respectively
and chapter 9 opens the door to
computational phenotyping in terms of
some of the framings and opportunities
and challenges associated with modeling
empirical data
and uses of generative models for
statistical ends
so
more review on the first five
then a little bit on six speed through
seven and eight
self-evidencing as a first principle
not reward as a first principle
self-evidencing relative to some
active generative model as the first
principle
if you're on board
enjoy the ride
go back to chapter one read the book
if you're not convinced about
self-evidencing
as a first principle then there might be
some other approaches still go back to
chapter one and read it but once
somebody is on board
that perception and action being in the
same game
of self-evidencing
with a common information theoretic
currency
information related currency
active inference is that model
we do more than integrate perception and
action we don't homogenize them or or
blend them it's actually very clear what
they are but they're in the same game
and they have that same currency
and when we take that kind of a first
principles approach
it's compatible with these kinds of
inactivists
languages
but also
we
have
extensible ways to deal with other
diverse cognitive phenomena
like memory and attention
how do we deal with all these cognitive
phenomena in different systems with
different architectures and so on
well
everything is reflected through
structural or parametric
specification in the generative model
part one
part two generative models are evaluated
according to their free energies just
like any other Bayesian model
part two
so part one
say what you mean
in the generative model if it's not in
the generative model
it's just a secret in your mind
part two
if it's a Bayesian graph generative
model
then
we have techniques for model fitting
message passing
variational free energy and so on
so step one
don't make it a secret
step two FIT the model
like all models can be fit
super clear super powerful sometimes
hard to even convey
because it's so removed
from the presentation
of other cognitive science approaches
earlier
shank and the neat scruffy distinction
was introduced chapter one probably
active inference is not reifying
the nouns in English associated with
cognitive functions and trying to Cobble
them together
it's not a mosaic
it starts
from a unified perspective
and then elaborates or differentiates
in order to realize cognitive functions
but not by reifying them as modular
items that can be like picked up and
moved
again really key different than how it's
often addressed in other areas
probably a lot of philosophical depth
that could be explored not for today in
these jamesian categories
when we take that perspective
of starting with a unified whole iguana
a whole conceptual iguana
pull behavioral ethologist looking at
naguana
situation figure 9.1
then
we can understand so much better
structural and parametric similarities
and differences amongst different
cognitive models
we couldn't ask for a better way to do
it
if one appears it'll be a gift
but within
some pretty broad considerations
this
ethologists set up
is the one that we want for this making
a map about a map
and that's why
[Music]
ramstead and friston are such vociferous
advocates
for everything that we're seeing
the trade-offs amongst all kinds of
behavior one example being like
so-called explore exploit but all kinds
of cognitive trade-offs like forgetting
versus uh attention and
um risk versus
Etc
all of those
when approached as if they could be
these modular Standalone patterns
they are only reified through
investigation
rather than seeing these trade-offs
these predo-optimal trade-offs or these
manifolds have measured outcomes
rather than looking at the generative
model or a generative process that gives
rise to those manifolds
the manifold becomes reified as if there
was somehow a fundamental trade-off
between exploration and exploitation
when
depending on the regularities of the
niche and the affordances available to
the agents
those two might literally not be at odds
like what if you're just munching
through a field and there's um food
everywhere and you're just munching all
around
then there's no trade-off
so the trade-off is not fundamental to
these English words
it's about the interplay of the
generative model and the generative
process
which is our stance on everything
it's about the interplay between the
generative model as specified and the
generative process as specified
trade-offs don't exist in some other
abstract space
Beyond helping us at the
um
algorithmic layer here using Mars
taxonomy
we can also peek deeper into neural
computations and representations
signatures and so on
and here one can look at the work in SPM
in human neuroimaging and Sensor Fusion
and then build from there to incorporate
more sophisticated generative models and
action policies
now they're going to sketch a psychology
textbook
and this is where the earlier points
about 10 providing a lot of the
conceptual and historical context
is very salient
because these are the kinds of things
these are the the buoys or the signposts
that other people are going to be
familiar with
when they're wanting to know more about
octave
foreign
they introduce and discard
the sandwich model
and they highlight
the Primacy or the centrality of the
generative model
that explicitly makes predictive
and arguably goal directed but at the
very least predictive
dimensions of that model
absolutely primary
what imperative is Downstream
of the Primacy of prediction
self-evidencing
at the stimuli processing level
we see predictive coding predictive
processing
at a slightly slower which we the time
scale which we could model with a nested
model
we see learning neuromodulators
slower inference
and action is fundamentally embedded
within this process
for example icicades moving across a
page
this allows
the Dual
drives
which epistemic and pragmatic are one
decomposition of free Energies
expected free energy in this case
to integrate the sort of preference
oriented
gold realizing
and information oriented
components to behavior
predictive processing
what is there to say this is basically
plus action
and live stream 43
makes that pretty clear
the paper in live stream 43.
perception
you don't see with your eyes you see
with your mind
what you're seeing is generated
you're not getting the video camera Raw
Feed
That's a classic idea
Maria did great work reporting on the
history of these ideas in 43.0
Bayesian brain
putting that perceptual predictive
paradigm
into the jargon or into the methodology
of Bayesian statistics
it's just a last name Bayesian
statistics is
modern statistics
they return to predictive coding
action
action is another variable
we make predictions about action we have
priors on action
we have a policy prior
and then we update it or not into the
policy posterior
that's that basal ganglia chapter 5.
so action selection
planning as inference is just another
variable
and so all of the meta
on Bayesian statistics
is going to hold whether we're talking
about inference on perception
the kind of under part of figure 4.3 or
inference on action the upper part of
figure 4.3
within each of the GMS
and that leads to some different
thinking about for example motor control
and uh interactionism versus
instructionism
[Music]
um
sensory attenuation
and all these other diverse
motor phenomena
also being integrated because we took a
first principles perspective
we didn't choose to reify sensory
attenuation as some discrete phenomena
rather we chose to model action as a
kind of inference action selection as a
kind of inference
that in a bodied agent takes in the
niche
and that led to a complete
um
collusion
with sensory attenuation as an empirical
phenomena
this isn't falling out of reward
learning
this isn't falling out of Excel
spreadsheets
idea motor theory and various other
paradigms have been proposed to
understand this bi-directionality
with action and effect so it's like a
little bit jarring to read because it's
kind of
um not in the active inference ontology
how it's being stated by them of course
but
many of the terms are resemblant enough
and
active inference encompasses it and
bolsters it
and provides ways to compute message
passing all of that
anything that's just like a way of
thinking it's like that's cool it's a
cool way of thinking can you do message
passing on that
so that's where the pragmatic value
comes into play
there's a variety of ways of thinking
about the action perception Loop there's
the tote test operate test exit
there's the UDA observe Orient decide
act and so on
and broadly
we're talking about the same kinds of
Agents
and active inference helps us understand
Frameworks that have often been
qualitatively applied
or quantitatively applied
to cybernetic systems
on the inbound optimal perceptual
processing is a signal processing
challenge
on the outbound optimal action selection
has been approached from this area of
control theory
we're unifying the inbound signal
processing and the outbound control
theoretic dimensions of cybernetics into
a unified imperative
how exactly they're balanced in a given
realization of a model
that is for the researcher to specify
not for the framework to be opinionated
upon
but we have the grammar and the space
to
have um
blind systems that act wisely or not
and perceptive systems that act
intelligently or not or whatever
the framework is not going to have an
opinion on those kinds of
balances in their specifics
special cases of the unified imperative
for example the expected free energy
when there is no epistemic value to gain
fully observable setting
perfect understanding of the
consequences of the self in the world
or on the other hand a setting where
there's a lot to learn but there's no
pragmatic value all outcomes are equally
preferred
special cases of decision making
map onto special cases of the unified
imperative
so just from a very narrow and Technical
View
active inference is simply a
generalization of for example Bayesian
decision Theory
reinforcement learning but let's see how
they differ
they differ in a usage of a few ontology
terms
they talk about model based and model
free RL
policy gradient methods a lot of
similarities of course it'd be awesome
to have a notebook where we can compare
and contrast side by side
action planning as inference it's just
another variable
and other people have suggested it
approximate Bayesian computation bounded
rationality base optimal Behavior
including pathology
these are all
totally plausible for us to explore
valence emotion motivation these are
quite diffuse and complex cognitive
phenomena
there are ways to specify them in
generative models
doesn't mean that octave tells us what
these things are
they're just strings of English letters
they're just pixels on a screen
but we can use them semiotically and
build cognitive models that have these
kinds of patterns
homeostasis of course considered broadly
is critical to the high road
and so we have a lot about how in Tarot
and exteroceptive inference interact in
order to support persistence
attention
and salience relevance realization these
are core for the epistemic drive
homeostasis can broadly be seen as being
about pragmatic value
whereas epistemic Dynamics are about
epistemic value
different cognitive modes
again not just being proposed ad hoc by
a TED talk or pop psychology book or a
research paper
starting from a solid grounding
and then differentiating
the generalized framework
to embody these patterns not to reify
the patterns as actual phenomena that
then need to be plugged and played
and we know there are so many open
directions
applications to human scale social
cultural systems
integration with contemporary machine
learning systems
embodied cyber physical systems
sometimes called robotics
and
just like the cover of the book was the
one ring not to rule them all
here we have the Tolkien quote
and
the journey comes to a conclusion unless
you read on to the appendices
they proposed an introduction
and at least from the author's View
you will pursue active inference in some
form
so
in our closing minutes
how does this strike either of you
fellows what are your Reflections upon
completing the book one or more times
yeah I'm very much convinced about this
idea and I guess I will pursue this for
some time to come
to
lots of work to fit the data into this
whole thing
but that's my
my attention
and thanks very much for your very
insightful guidance through this book it
was extremely helpful thank you thank
you so much
thank you Michael
Ali
upon this and reading of the textbook
what is standing out to you more and
more or differently
in fact more generally I feel that with
each
reading uh kind of nested markup
blankets is building up
uh inside my I mean the cognition
framework because
with each reading I become much aware of
some of the connections between
different parts and different sections
of the theory
which I was not aware on the first
reading at all so hopefully this growing
nested markup blanket will continue to
grow with a feature reading as well
awesome
yes
what to even say it was a great
cohort we spanned
from the end of 2022
on through
April and 23
um
and that brings this cohort to a
conclusion
so thanks a lot to
cohort to
next week we'll return
and it won't be recorded we'll just be
talking about feedback project ideas and
so on
and um
thanks again